Finding Aid for University Health Service (University of Michigan) Records 1912-1998.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University Health Service (University of Michigan) records 1912-1998 1970-1998
University of Michigan. University Health Service.
Campus health service for University of Michigan faculty, staff and students. Records include annual reports; collected historical papers; reports of survey findings and questionnaire results on health service related issues; planning documents; and clippings; and photographs.
87177 Bimu C510 2
7.0 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Records were received from the University Health Service (Donor no. 4607 ) beginning in 1968.
The records are open for research.
A campus health service was established in 1912, in response to requests by faculty and students for a student infirmary similar to those already in existence at several other American universities. The University Health Service officially opened its doors in 1913 in a converted residence on the current site of Burton Memorial Tower. The facility was staffed by two physicians (one male and one female), a nurse, and a clerk who responded to the health needs of over 5,500 students. Initially the Health Service provided only ambulatory care with more seriously ill patients receiving in-room house calls or referrals to the University Hospital. In 1921, the Health Service became a unit of the new Division of Hygiene and Public Health and was relocated to the Children's Annex of the former Homeopathic Hospital. The new location offered 20 inpatient beds, as well as space for offices, x-ray, laboratory, and pharmacy services.
Throughout the 1920s the Health Service was expanded to include new services, departments and clinics. Dentistry and surgery services were added in 1923, and a physiotherapy department was opened the following year. Mental hygiene services began in 1927 with a part-time social worker and volunteer psychiatrist. In 1928, the ear, nose and throat, dermatology, and allergy clinics were added to the growing specialized services. A dietitian joined the staff in 1933, bringing the Health Service staff total to nearly 50 members.
In 1939 the current University Health Service building on Fletcher Street was constructed. The new building, occupied in 1940, was specifically designed to meet the particular needs of the Health Service, including 65 inpatient beds. A decade later, the staff of the UHS had grown to approximately 140 employees.
An immunization clinic was established in 1969, and in 1971 the Gynecology/Contraception Clinic was separated from the main medical clinic to meet the health needs of women students.
The 1970s and 1980s saw a move away from inpatient activity toward providing public health information on campus. Ambulatory care continued to increase, but lack of patients forced the closure of the infirmary in 1983. The latter half of the 1980s saw continuing growth of public information programs, including use of the campus computing network. One such program is the Peer Health Aide program, which trains peer educators to deliver programs on substance abuse, nutrition, contraception, and safe sex.
More information can be found at the official UHS Web Site: http://www.uhs.umich.edu
Directors of the University Health Service
1913-1917 Howard H. Cummings
1917-1955 Warren E. Forsythe
1955-1967 Morley B. Beckett
1968-1980 Robert E. Anderson
1981-1999 Caesar Briefer
1999- Robet A. Winfield
The records of the University Health Service (UHS) date from 1912 to 1998, but primarily document the period 1970-1998. The records reflect the programming and educational activities of the UHS, its changes in both physical and organizational structure and its evolution from a tiny student-service provider of emergency care to a multi-department health care facility serving students and university employees in a number of emergency and preventative, and health maintenance capacities.
The UHS collection is divided into nine series: Historical, Memoranda, Programming, Proposals, Publications, Reports, Surveys, Topical, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
AIDS (Disease)--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Prevention.; Public health--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. University Health Service.; Health education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Health attitudes--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Substance abuse--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Prevention.
Contributors:
Vaughan, Victor C. (Victor Clarence), 1851-1929.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Historical File
  The Historical file contains a folder of miscellaneous early documents, which is a small group of the earliest UHS records, including a 1912 "Plan for a University Physician and Infirmary" presented to President Hutchins by the Committee on Investigation of Infirmary Conditions at Other Universities, along other documents pertaining to the genesis of the unit. A few examples of historical summaries from various points in time follows.
  - Miscellaneous Early Documents 1912, 1930 (Box 1)
  - General History
    - 1937 (Box 1)
    - 1962-1981 (Box 1)
  - Sports and Athletics 1979-1980 (Box 1)
- Memoranda
  Memoranda are communications within the agency to inform staff of policy, procedure and items of interest. Examples include the 1956 founding of a Pharmacy Committee, a 1958 announcement of a new $2.00 per visit student fee, and a 1960 change in pre-registration examination requirements for new students.
  - Memoranda 1956-1965 (Box 1)
  - Memoranda 1964-1967 (Box 1)
- Programming
  Programming details various Health education and outreach activities, including nutritional programs in dormitories, conferences and workshops on relationships, body image, sexual assault prevention, smoking cessation and the development of the peer health aide program.
  - Breast Health circa 1993 (Box 1)
  - Computer Systems
    - UM-UHS Computer Health Network 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Computerized Health Information Program (CHIP) 1987-1993 (Box 1)
    - "Tripod," Computer Assisted Instruction Link 1995 (Box 1)
  - Contraceptive Education
    - Condom Sense 1992 (Box 1)
    - Contraceptive Issues Task Force 1987 (Box 1)
    - General
      - 1982-1983 (Box 1)
      - 1986-1988, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1990-1996, 10 folders (Box 1)
    - Male Contraceptive Education Manual 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Personal Choice: Guide to the Selection of Birth Control 1986-1988 (Box 1)
    - Program Evaluation 1980 (Box 1)
    - Peer Education Manual (Box 1)
  - Coordinating Manual circa 1997 (Box 1)
  - Exploring Relationships Conference 1984 (Box 1)
  - "Festifall," 1984-1988 (Box 1)
  - Health Educator 1975-1980 (Box 1)
  - Health and Lifestyle Course 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Health Promotion 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Markley Wellness Program 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Measles Immunization 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Nutrition Education 1985 (Box 1)
  - Peer Education
    - Body Image 1993-1998, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - General 1989, 1990-1991, 1992, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Health Service Peer Educator Multicultural Issues Agenda 1994 (Box 2)
    - Stress and Time Management 1995-1996 (Box 2)
  - Peer Health Aide
    - General 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Research Proposal 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - "Run for the Health of It" (5k run) 1981-1985 (Box 2)
  - Self Care Program 1982 (Box 2)
    (2 folders)
  - Sexual Assault Education and Prevention 1984-1986, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Smoking Cessation
    - General, circa 1990-1993 (Box 2)
    - Say No to Nicotine 1986-1988, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Smoke-Free, 1989-1995, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Task Force on Alcohol and Other Drugs 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - Time Management Presentations circa 1992 (Box 2)
- Proposals
  Proposals are applications for educational program funding support, submitted to university entities such as the University of Michigan Substance Abuse Center, and public sources such as Washtenaw County. UHS responses to public concern with growing issues, such as alcohol abuses on campus, are reflected. Also included in this series is a 1938 proposal for a new facility, which documents rationale, plans and budgeting for this undertaking. This became the Fletcher St. facility which still houses UHS.
  - Proposal and Planning of New Building 1938-1939, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Proposal for the Expansion of Health Services to Non-Student Spouses 1972 (Box 2)
  - Cohort Study of Health Care Utilization and Behavior 1981 (Box 2)
  - Health Promotion Proposals, circa 1982-1985 (Box 2)
  - Substance Abuse Education, circa 1986 (Box 2)
  - Alcohol Education Program 1989 (Box 2)
  - Healthier Choices: A Worksite Health Risk Management Pilot Program for Housing Division Employees 1990 (Box 2)
  - Fund for the Improvement of Post-secondary Education (FIPSE) Grant Proposal 1993 (Box 2)
- Publications
  Publications is divided into five subseries: Articles and Academic Publications, Newsletters, Pamphlets and Information Sheets, UHS Procedures, and Miscellaneous.
  - Articles and Scholarly Publications
    Articles and Academic Publications comprises a articles about the university health service or written by university health service staff members, including a copy of an article on influenza co-authored by Jonas Salk and autographed by him.
    - Antihistamines 1951-1956 (Box 2)
    - Health and Hygiene Education 1933-1935 (Box 2)
    - Influenza 1944-1947 (Box 2)
      (includes offprint inscribed by Jonas Salk)
    - Mental Hygiene 1936-1955 (Box 2)
    - Tuberculosis and Respiratory Disease 1932-1936 (Box 2)
    - University Medicine 1919-1958 (Box 2)
    - Women's Health 1934-1955 (Box 2)
  - Newsletters
    Newsletters comprises a single issue of a 1972 newsletter and issues of a newsletter for students and faculty Good Health News. Researchers interested in UHS's employee newsletter will find it separately cataloged at Fimu B28 H4, while the UHS Bulletin can be found at Fimu B28 H434 B936. (See also separately cataloged items)
    - Healer, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Good Health News, 1990-1997 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets and Information Sheets (Box 3)
    By far, the largest subseries of Publications is Pamphlets and Information Sheets, which comprises several generations of topical informational pamphlets and handouts developed by UHS staff. Many of the files contain not only copies of the pamphlets, but documents related to their creation and editing. These pamphlets may be of particular interest to researchers studying changes in public health concerns and health education, particularly with respect to sexually transmitted diseases including HIV/AIDS and contraception.
    - Acne (Box 3)
    - AIDS / HIV
      - General (Box 3)
      - Counseling and Testing (Box 3)
    - Alcohol (Box 3)
    - Allergies (Box 3)
    - Ann Arbor Area Health Resources (Box 3)
    - Antibiotics / Bacteria (Box 3)
    - Athlete's Foot (Box 3)
    - Back Care and Ergonomics (Box 3)
    - Barrier Methods (Box 3)
      (Contraception)
    - Blood Cholesterol (Box 3)
    - Blood Tests (Box 3)
    - Breasts (Box 3)
    - Caffeine (Box 3)
    - Canker Sores (Box 3)
    - Chicken Pox (Box 3)
    - Chlamydia (Box 3)
    - Clinicians (Box 3)
    - Cold Sores (Box 3)
    - Common Cold (Box 3)
    - Contraception and Safer Sex (Box 3)
    - Cryotherapy (Box 3)
    - Cystitis (Box 3)
    - Dandruff (Box 3)
    - Diaphragms (Box 3)
    - Diet Pills (Box 3)
    - Eating Disorders (Box 3)
    - Endometriosis (Box 3)
    - Exercise (Box 3)
    - Eye Care (Box 3)
    - Faculty and Staff (Box 3)
    - Genital Warts (Box 3)
    - Giant Papillary Conjunctivitis (Box 3)
    - Gonorrhea (Box 3)
    - Gynecology (Box 3)
    - Health Promotion and Education (Box 3)
    - Health Service Fee (Box 3)
    - Heart (Box 3)
    - Hemorrhoids (Box 3)
    - Hepatitis (Box 3)
    - Herpes (Box 3)
    - Hypoglycemia (Box 3)
    - Hypothermia (Box 3)
    - Influenza (Box 3)
    - International Students (Box 3)
    - Lactose Intolerance (Box 3)
    - M Care (Box 3)
    - Measles, Mumps and Rubella (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Mononucleosis (Box 3)
    - Non-Gonococcal / Non-Specific Urethritis (Box 3)
    - Non-Prescription Drugs (Box 3)
    - Norplant (Box 3)
    - Nutrition (Box 3)
      (see also Vegetarians)
    - Osteoperosis (Box 4)
    - Patient Feedback (Box 4)
    - Patient Financial Information (Box 4)
    - Patient Rights and Responsibilities (Box 4)
    - Periodic Health Appraisal Unit (Box 4)
    - Pharmacy / Formulary (Box 4)
    - Physical Examinations (Box 4)
    - Physical Therapy (Box 4)
    - The Pill (Box 4)
    - Pregnancy Testing (Box 4)
    - Radiology Tests / Examinations (Box 4)
    - Sexuality and Sex Education (Box 4)
    - Sexually Transmissible Diseases (Box 4)
      (STDs)
    - Sigmoidoscopy (Box 4)
    - Smoking (Box 4)
    - Stress / Anxiety (Box 4)
    - Students (Box 4)
    - University Health Service (Box 4)
      (Generic)
    - Vaginitis (Box 4)
    - Vegetarians (Box 4)
    - Vitamins (Box 4)
    - Warts (Box 4)
    - Weight Control / Loss (Box 4)
  - UHS Procedures
    UHS Procedures includes several documents published by UHS for communicating policies and procedures to staff. Miscellaneous comprises a number of publications that did not fall under one of the other categories, such as a 1972 flyer titled Is Health Care a Rip-Off?
    - General Directions for Procedures 1952-1953 (Box 4)
    - Guidelines for Control of Infections 1969 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Architecture Plans 1939, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Calendars
      - Multicultural 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - Forms (special) 1941 (Box 4)
    - Health Service Bulletin, no date (Box 4)
      (early)
    - Is Health Care a Rip-Off?, 1972 (Box 4)
    - New Student Letters 1983-1997 (Box 4)
    - Philosophy and Mission Statements, no date (Box 4)
    - Twenty-fifth Anniversary 1938 (Box 4)
- Reports
  Reports include UHS monthly and annual reports for much of the 20th century, as well as committee reports, program reviews, and planning and evaluation documents. Some of these have become proposals and actual new projects, and others, such as the 1969 Committee on a New Building Facility, end at the reporting phase.
  - Annual
    - University Health Service
      - 1938-1975 (Box 4)
        (24 folders)
      - 1976-1985 (Box 5)
        (10 folders)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 5)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 5)
    - Health Promotion / Education 1978-1992 (Box 5)
      (13 folders)
  - Monthly 1917-1967 (Box 5)
    (7 folders)
  - Topical
    - AIDS Awareness Week final report 1994, 1997 (Box 5)
    - Adequacy of Service to Disabled Students 1978 (Box 5)
    - An Analysis of Hygiene Administration and Education at UM 1937 (Box 5)
    - Committee on Building New Facilities 1969 (Box 5)
    - Committee on the Costs of Medical Care 1932 (Box 5)
      (a comparative study of various schools, including UM)
    - Committee Report on Long Range Planning for UHS 1971 (Box 5)
    - Committees 1958-1968 (Box 5)
    - Facility Feasibility Study (Houlihan & Associates Architects) 1985 (Box 5)
    - Health Education at University of Michigan Health Service 1971 (Box 5)
    - Health Services Advisory Committee 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - Health Services Study Committee 1968 (Box 5)
    - Motivational Factors Affecting Patient Attrition in a Weight Loss Program, circa 1982 (Box 5)
    - Multicultural Awareness Committee (Box 5)
    - Personnel Organization Review Medical/Central Campus Division 1979 (Box 5)
    - Program Statement 1987 (Box 5)
    - Tuberculosis Control Program 1931-1951, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Tuberculosis In Our Colleges 1947-1948 (Box 5)
    - University Health Services Evaluation 1989 (Box 6)
    - University Task Force on Student Counseling 1976 (Box 6)
    - Urgent Care Study 1986 (Box 6)
    - X-Ray 1940-1950 (Box 6)
- Surveys
  The Surveys series preserves efforts to assess and measure student health care knowledge, health practices, and patient satisfaction. Most of the surveys are small samples targeting narrow audiences such as peer education audiences, although a few surveys attempt to address campus-wide perceptions and practices on issues such as AIDS.
  - AIDS Survey (School of Public Health) 1989 (Box 6)
  - Annual Health Service Evaluation 1982 (Box 6)
  - Behavioral Modification Program 1985 (Box 6)
  - Dress and Manner of Health Care Providers 1982 (Box 6)
  - Faculty and Staff Survey 1983 (Box 6)
  - Gynecology Clinic Patient Satisfaction 1970-1971 (Box 6)
  - HIV/AIDS Education Session Client Survey 1993 (Box 6)
  - Medical History Questionnaire and Data 1983-1989 (Box 6)
  - Monitoring of Patient Care at UHS 1981 (Box 6)
  - OSHA Examination Program Patient Satisfaction 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - Ostrow Survey (AIDS, Alcohol, Contraception) 1987-1988 (Box 6)
  - Pediatric Interest Survey 1983 (Box 6)
  - Pharmacy Patient Satisfaction 1985 (Box 6)
  - Program Evaluation Committee Questionnaire 1978 (Box 6)
  - Radiology Patient Satisfaction Survey 1985 (Box 6)
  - Smoking Survey
    - 1974 (Box 6)
    - 1989 (Box 6)
  - Student Health Advisory Committee (SHAC) Telephone Survey 1982 (Box 6)
  - Student Health Interest 1981-1982 (Box 6)
  - Student Health Practices 1982 (Box 6)
  - Student Health Survey 1986 (Box 6)
  - Suggestion Form Survey 1968 (Box 6)
  - VD Clinic 1980-1981 (Box 6)
- Topical
  The Topical files combine special topics, such as guidelines to control infections; files of administrative nature, such as goal statements and organizational charts; extra-organizational documents such as the Student Advisory Committee; and records of particular people and events related in various ways to UHS and its development.
  - Accreditation 1973, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - By-Laws of the Medical Staff of UHS 1982 (Box 6)
  - Central Appointment Office 1981-1982 (Box 6)
  - Clinic Distinctions 1982 (Box 6)
  - Clippings 1972-1983 (Box 6)
  - Community Health Education Committee (CHEC) 1984-1990, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Executive Committee Meetings 1968-1972 (Box 6)
  - Floor Plan of Fletcher St. Facility 1987 (Box 6)
  - Goal Statements 1973-1975 (Box 6)
  - Greater Washtenaw Area Tel-Med 1987-1991 (Box 6)
  - Guidelines for Control of Infections 1969 (Box 6)
  - Gynecology Clinic Information Sheets undated (Box 6)
  - Health Rights and Responsibilities of Members of the College Community, circa 1974 (Box 6)
  - Health Services Building 1939 (Box 6)
  - Infection Control Committee 1968-1970 (Box 6)
  - Nakamura, Dr. Yuko 1950 (Box 6)
  - National Conference on College Hygiene 1936, 1947, 1954 (Box 6)
  - Organizational Charts 1979-1981 (Box 6)
  - Patient Eligibility Statement 1988 (Box 6)
  - Renovation 1987 (Box 6)
  - Rules and Regulations of the UHS 1982 (Box 6)
  - Seventy-fifth Anniversary 1988 (Box 6)
  - Student Health Advisory Committee (SHAC) 1979-1980, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Student Records Policy (Box 6)
  - World War II 1942-1944
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series contains the UHS scrapbook, several historical photographs and various photo records of contemporary health promotion activities. Included is a sequence of 42 photographs taken in 1961 detailing the steps and diagnostic equipment involved in the periodic health examination. An oversize album portrays UHS staff from 1913 to 1956-57. Several copy prints illustrate early student health exams. Prints and negatives portray a health run, and staff (group and individuals) during the 75th anniversary in 1988. The UHS scrapbook contains newspaper clippings depicting people and events from 1967 to 1982. The series also includes an outsize folder of posters that advertise UHS services, including its specialty clinics and drug treatment facilities.
  - Buildings circa 1913-1980s (Box 7)
    - Exterior (Box 7)
    - Interior (Box 7)
  - Exhibits 1937, 1988 (Box 7)
  - "Festifall," 1987 (Box 7)
  - Health Exam Sequence 1961, 42 mounted photographs (Box 7)
  - Health Service Floor Plans (glass slides) 1939 (Box 7)
  - Negatives (Box 7)
  - "Health Service Staff, 1913-1957" (Volume 1)
    (Outsize Album (B 172 4))
  - Photographs, not dated (Box 7)
  - "Run for the Health of It," 1981 (Box 7)
  - 75th Anniversary 1988 (Box 7)
  - Slides 1980 (Box 7)
  - Staff, circa 1913-1980s (Box 7)
  - Treatment and Examination, circa 1920-1980s (Box 7)
  - UHS Scrapbook 1967 (Box 7)
  - UHS Promotional Posters (Folder Bimu C510)